Thank you.
I have a hope that came out.
We were out before, we were in the green room before and somebody said, I hope this goes
well.
And we didn't sound very hopeful.
I said, I'm not very hopeful.
We are right.
You talked about we're in Advent.
It's Adventist Latin is for anticipation.
And we're looking forward in anticipation and that anticipation is hope.
And it's difficult for Christians, I think, to live in hope.
We more often talk about our faith as faith, right?
And that's been around since the 1500s.
We've been definitely the exact same way that we celebrated as 1500s.
That means 800 generations of Christians have done this, right?
Where in the four weeks leading up to Christmas, we remember what it was like to look forward
to the coming of Christ, right?
And we, so we spent, what, 14 weeks in John where we're sort of retrospectively looking
back at the life of Christ.
And the next four weeks, we're spending four weeks remembering looking forward at the coming
of Christ, to the coming of Christ.
And the hope that they have, let me see.
This chunk of the Bible, this chunk of the Bible, this chunk of the Bible is one of the things
that, this chunk is everybody looking forward to getting finished, right?
And then there's this bit at the end, which is what, you know, after Christ's been, right?
So for all of this time, it was just anticipation, just hope or despair.
Those are the options, right?
And eventually, it was fulfilled, but today, we sometimes, you hear away from the vote part
because you don't want to return the ground with the football, right?
You don't want to do discipline, you don't want to, yeah, okay.
I thought I might be too old for this audience, but no, okay.
So, about the time, that's interesting, about the time Advent was documented and studied
as a celebration, Augustine Tickle, St. Augustine, somebody asked him,
can you give me a little handbook on what Christian is all about?
I need to go to the faith, and can you tell me what it's about?
He wrote something called the E-Koridian Unfaithbook,
and the E-Koridians, the Greek word, plain handbook.
And so, in this, a little piece of book, it's 3 and 50,
I knew there was sort of nine paragraphs of introductory information.
There were five paragraphs on life, three paragraphs on hope,
and 105 of unfaith, right?
Because we just oppose you that way.
We want to live in the moment.
You guys are expressing faith in the chairs you're sitting in right now,
because faith is always in the moment.
You believe to hold in love.
But hope is in the future, and you can be a fool of your hope, right?
We have, for the last six weeks, we've been having a passage class on judging,
and we've been reading through the insanity and the injustice and the retributive times of this horror,
and everybody's looking through this particular point in Jewish history.
The promise land, the people in the promise land had fallen forward of the promise,
and they had lost sight of hope, right?
And it was a time when somebody would rise up and sort of create justice.
They lasted in vengeance, and then someone else would keep vengeance on the vengeful,
and vengeance eventually.
This is likely, it's a circular filing squad, you know,
where we're tearing down the guy that tore me down until they were torn up to their promised land,
and the promise was gone.
And the young men were destroyed unnecessarily.
The land was destroyed.
The young women were kidnapped and raped,
and it was this terrible time of lawlessness.
Here, the seed of the future hope was missing,
because hope is in the seed always, right?
But we haven't talked about the already, but not yet.
The teacher that we're given over and over in Scripture is of a seed.
You plant the seed.
You have the seed.
Last time I went through speaking, I said,
Christ, try to curl a seed in the ground.
It dies, and from that grows a great clop of more seeds.
Corey, last week, talked about,
if you abide in me,
and I abide in you, right?
You abide in us under me.
You're my disciples.
If you love me, you abide in us under me.
Do you remember in, um,
Corinthians 7, 15, uh, 8?
The other way that you say,
you know you're my disciples if you have loved the Lord and for another,
we're abiding in you by them.
You also know you're my disciples if, in 15, 8,
my Father is glorified by this,
that you bear much fruit and choose to be my disciples.
Well, like, fruit, fruit.
Where's my God knows?
What is it?
Seeds.
The hope of the future of the plant is in the seed,
bearing fruit when he's having seeds,
which can fall off and grow more,
extend the vine over space and time.
In the time of Judges, there's a story of Reef,
which is what we're going to talk about this morning.
Reef, um,
in the first,
this is a little four-chapter book
that happened in the midst of all this chaos and lawlessness.
And the opening phrase tells us
that there was a famine in the land.
And so not only were they living in a famine
where the promise had been lost
and it was lawlessness and it was frightening,
but also getting these fruit,
the ground itself had lost the capacity for hope, right?
There was nothing in the future for these people.
And so in the opening, um,
verses of Reef, um,
we have a small family of two parents and two young children
who just abandoned their inherited element to go to Moab.
So they leave their inheritance behind the promise that was given to their ancestors
and they go to Moab,
which is a culture that, uh, practiced child sacrifice.
Uh, much of the history of Israel was about being fruitful and worth upon,
protecting the family of them,
and moving into Moab,
they had a habit of sacrificing young children to the gods
and helping to break in the ground and fertile.
Uh, an obvious side effect to that is research through an algae seed, right?
Um, there was a selfish culture, obviously,
well, arguably, um,
but the living and the being able
improved a lot at the expense of the vulnerable and weak.
And this is where our,
the heroes of our stories go.
They abandon the inheritance of this culture.
And the, um,
the children, uh,
they're there for about two years.
The, the two sons grow up,
marry wives of that culture,
which is, you know, forbidden.
And, uh,
then a point comes through.
And their attempt at saving their person, uh,
is failed.
And then the husband and the two sons die.
And Naomi, the mother,
is left with two women that she's not even really related to anymore.
The two daughters and all his lost sons.
Uh, the essence of the time,
your legal standing and your social status
were decided by the house that you were in,
the dad,
the father's household.
So, if you wanted to buy land,
if you wanted to inherit,
if you wanted to go to the court,
it was done,
the,
the laws were all organized through the house.
And Naomi no longer has a house.
She's a foreigner,
in a foreign land,
with no house.
She's not,
she has a zero legal standing.
And she has no family that can,
no hope for the future.
Okay.
And so,
she told her daughter-in-laws,
sorry about this,
um,
put you in an awkward spot.
Uh,
you can just go back to your father's household
for you to restart your lives.
Uh,
one of them says,
that makes sense in Reese's.
The other one that you read,
has this moment of incredible kindness.
Uh,
in verse 11 of chapter 1,
Naomi,
uh,
Naomi says to,
read through children,
why should you go with me?
Have I yet any sons in my womb
that may have been your husband?
Like,
there's no household that you can live in
in the future.
Like,
return my daughters.
Go,
for I'm too old to have a husband myself.
I'm too old to get around me,
so she's saying.
Um,
if I,
if I said I was having hope,
meaning hope for someone,
I should even have an,
even if I had a husband today,
and were able to bear with someone,
would you wait around for him to be great?
Um,
would you therefore refrain from there?
No,
my God,
it's too hard,
it's harder for me than for you,
uh,
for the hand of the Lord
has gone forth against me.
So,
I think many of us may be
in this moment,
uh,
the book of Job,
God said,
I mean,
where,
we should have gone real wrong,
and we're pretty sure God's against us.
David felt this way,
my God,
why did you suspect me?
It was written by David,
um,
in Psalm 22.
Um,
Naomi,
she is
childless,
she has no grandchildren,
she has no social standards,
she's standing,
she's alone,
in a foreign land,
no inheritance,
and so she's seen
in the times of the fear
that we maybe have never
quite gotten to her level.
But I have,
I heard a great quote recently
by, um,
Jared Anderson,
who's a poet.
He said,
we seldom admit
the seductive comfort
of hopelessness,
that saves
this ambiguity.
It has an answer
for every question,
there's just no hope.
Hope only at the end
of the message.
If it might all work out,
when we have things
to do,
we must,
we must weather
the possibility
of happiness.
Right?
It's all you bring
on the back
every time.
You have to teach
something.
You have to believe
in the hope
in the future
because Naomi's
past the point
of being able
to do that.
Right?
She's ready
to just give up.
In response,
though,
Ruth,
who has a clear
path ahead of her,
she's going to go back
to her father's house.
In verse 20 says,
I'm sorry,
not in verse 20,
verse 16 says,
don't urge me
to leave you
or come back
and follow me.
Where you go,
I'll go.
Where I lodge,
you lodge,
I lodge.
Your people be my people.
You're God,
my God.
Where you guys,
I'll die.
I'm not going to let this old woman
run for awful long.
Right?
And by the way,
I see old woman,
she was probably 40.
She was feeling like an old woman.
She was feeling them.
Ruth had just been married,
had a child.
She got married
by my dad's children.
That's just who's
very newly married.
Right?
And of course,
Naomi was a generation
of the first.
They were probably
early 20s,
early 40s.
But Naomi and Ruth
felt that her life
was over.
And Naomi and Ruth
said,
no.
You know?
And she committed
to something in his life,
which is abandoning
her family,
abandoning her life,
abandoning her religion,
free to Naomi,
following the God
of Bethlehem,
which is when I was
really quick
for Bethlehem,
named Judah.
And going back
and doing a foreign
in a foreign land
with no legal
standing on her own.
No way to have money.
No household
to grow up in.
She'll be able
to exactly see
about Naomi in it,
but she's going to go
and stick it out with her.
And it's an incredibly,
in a moment
in the whole landscape
of child sacrifice
and all the horrors
of judges
and the lawlessness,
this is an incredible
moment of calmness.
Right?
And so Ruth goes back
with Naomi.
Naomi, by the way,
the name of Naomi,
what she only means,
you know?
Sweetness, right?
And Naomi,
and Naomi says,
since she gets back home,
don't call me sweet,
call me bitter.
And in verse 20,
don't call me bitter
for the Lord
who dealt,
but the Lord brought me,
I left school,
but the Lord brought me back empty.
Why do you call me
on me?
This Lord has witnessed
against me
and afflicted.
She's not ready
to be my need.
to believe there's any hope.
And you have to picture
what she says that.
Houses at the time
were rock structures
and you would have
your animals downstairs
and sort of a stable
and you would live
on the second floor
above before the heat
would rise
and you lived
in close proximity.
You didn't have
refrigerators,
you had the chickens
nearby the roof,
you had it,
you know,
the milk was right downstairs.
And you could protect
your animals
by closing in the bottom floor.
So,
these things all
in 10 years.
Some legend
that it was abandoned
has been fallow
for 10 years.
The house hasn't
been cared for.
So,
you have to picture
which was some sort
of wood structure
probably would have
been falling apart.
You have to picture
two satter women
that just walked
four days
around the dead seat
sitting on the dirt
floors
of a disheveled
rock structure
staring out
the broken door
as just leaves
in the dirt
once you say,
I don't call them
sweet,
you just call them
dirt.
The Lord
is fabulous.
They made it
back home,
but what's the point?
She doesn't have
the seed
to make them
go again
with the land.
She doesn't have
the manpower
because here's
no household.
Growing young men
to clean the land
was a really
important thing
back then.
She has no
options for that.
And they're just
sitting in
impossible situations,
but they're
surrounded by
the rest of
the family.
Right?
The other
stupid family
would have had
an alien in the
property
and it would be
an other family.
It's just at
the end of winter
to be on their
property.
It's just the
winter,
and the barley
harvest is
beginning.
So this is
around Easter
Passover time.
And the barley
harvest is just
started.
And you can see
the castle
property
sealed.
Right?
And in the
beginning of
chapter 2,
barley had
Tinsley,
her husband,
and his great
wife,
his name was
Boaz.
And it's very
likely that they
could have seen
Boaz's property
from those that
probably would have
been a joint
or a close
life if they
were close
things wrong.
And there's a
rule, a law,
back in the
time, that
paupers were
allowed to just
pick up whatever
was dropped in the
field.
So if I'm
gathering, if I'm
harvesting, and I
drop stuff, I
can't pick that
up.
That's now the
property of the
poor and the
destitute.
Right?
And if I'm using
the size to harvest
in a field, if I
come to an angle, I
can't take the time
to be all greedy
and put all the
stuff out of the
corn.
I have to leave
them.
That's the property
of the poor and
the destitute.
That was sort of
the welfare
project I was
against in the
law of Moses.
So Ruth is
told that she
can go glean.
She can go pick
up all the
leftovers in the
neighboring fields.
So that's what
she starts doing.
And we're
going to fast
forward through
it, but in
chapter 2, Boaz
notices her doing
this.
He's heard that
this woman at
great risk to
herself is taking
care of a
change woman
of her, and he
appreciates her.
So he brings
three beers, and
he gives her
lunch, and she
lets her drink
out of his
well, and he
tells his
guys, everyone
knows he's
living, you've
got to answer
to me.
And he says,
oh, by the
way, she's
going anywhere
she's not
supposed to
out in the
middle of the
field, it's
okay, and
drops an
extra for her.
So he's
like, what she's
done for
man.
And then, so
Ruth comes back
to the first
day with a
bundle, which
is like a
laundry basket
full of
grain, and
the only
man is
that ain't
normal, right?
And he's
like, what is
you green
today?
He's like,
oh, I'm not
just standing
in Boaz, he
was real nice.
He's like, okay,
keep going back
there, right?
He's a relative
of mine, he's
taking care of
me, I really
appreciate it.
And Boaz has
this wonderful
moment where he's
supposed to
read, oh, you
know, I
appreciate all you
doing for my
relative.
May the
Lord reward
your work and
your wages be
forcing the
Lord, the God
of Israel, under
his wings you
have come to
seek rescue.
So he
recognizes that
she has
accepted the
God of Israel
and she's an
adopted member
of this society.
She's not
going to follow
the God of
the Lord.
And he's
really gracious
to her and
says, you
know, God
will protect
you.
But, you
know how
James has
this true
religious
decision
court,
it's
care of
widows
and orphans
in their
distress,
right?
These are the
widows and
orphans.
Whereas, in
this time of
lawlessness, he's
taking care of
them, right?
He's going to
give God.
And he gives
you this blessing,
he says, God
bless you, he'll
take care of
you.
And then he
throws grain on
the ground for
you, right?
He's doing what
we're committed to
do in the New
Testament, right?
He's taking
your widows
and orphans
to stress, he's
blessing them, but
he's not
walking away and
saying, God
bless you,
somebody will
take care of
you.
He's asking
you to take
them apart.
And when he
says widows and
orphans, please
understand that
many of the
people that
are outside
the father's
house, the
people that
no longer
have a father's
house to
break them,
that's their
way of saying
the people
outside the
protection of
current social
structures, right?
The people that
can't take care of
themselves easily,
the real
troubling, that's
infestate
trouble, not
just widows
and orphans,
that's what
you realize
it's a
plan.
Make sense?
Okay.
So that's the
setup.
There's four
months passed
like this, from
the beginning of
the barley
harvest to the
end of the
wheat harvest.
And those
of you who
know the
story of
Reese, knows
that the
crux of the
story is in
chapter three,
where a man
who says,
boy, do I
have a good
idea for you.
If you
ever look
online at
internet
people commenting
something,
yeah,
it's a great
place to get
sociology.
If you
want to
sermon
and
commentary,
there's
going to
be a
whole
spectrum
of
explanation
what
happens
in
this
chapter,
from a
highly
symbolic
gesture
to a
highly
salacious
act,
right?
We're
going to
read it
right now
together and
then we'll
talk about
what it
actually
is.
So
Naomi says
to her
daughter-in-law,
my daughter
should not
seek security
for you so
that everything
will be well
with you.
Now,
verse 2,
is boris not
a tinsman
who's made
your,
what you do
or work
with?
Behold,
who runnows
barley at
the
dressing
floor
tonight.
So,
tonight's a
big
thing.
We know
where he's
going to
be tonight.
Wash
yourself
therefore,
anoint
yourself,
put on
your best
clothes,
good
items
of
dressing
floor,
but don't
make
yourself
known
until the
man is
going to
see
when he
drinking.
It
shall be
that when
he lies
down,
you'll
notice
where he
lies
down,
and go
uncover
his
feet,
lie
down,
and he
will
tell you
what
you
shall
do.
So,
there's a
number of
ways to
start to
go.
I will
say that
the way I
was taught
this to get
to Sunday
school was
when he
said to
Ruth,
I want
you to
get
junkied
up as
much as
you can,
wait until
the guy
is sleepy,
had a
little
wine,
is
deceptive
or anything,
go pull
up his
robe and
ask for
financial
advice.
That's
how it
was taught
to me.
There
are those
who want
to take
Ruth from
a solid
image by
sending
you to
a
holy
symbolic
ceremony.
If that
were the
case,
he would
not be
going by
the cover
of the
night,
he was
dressed
before it
would be
out in
the gates
where he
would be
going.
It's not
salacious,
protection makes
it clear that
Boavs
protects him,
and it
doesn't go
as far as
it could.
What you
have to
realize when
you read
this is how
vulnerable and
desperate
they are
in the
reason.
What he
did was
not
symbolic,
it wasn't
just for our
benefit today,
they were
desperate.
It wasn't
salacious,
it wasn't
coming to
room of
the
wife,
right on
the edge
of the
mouthful.
It was
doing
everything
he could.
And
verse 6,
we went
down to
the
dressing
floor and
did
according
to all
the
mother
law
and
commanded.
When
Boaz had
eaten
his
mouth
and
his
heart
was
merry,
he went
to lie
down
with the
end of
the
heap
of
ground
and
she
came
secretly
and
in front of
his feet
and lay
down.
So,
why is
Boaz,
first of all,
how did they
know where he
would be,
how did
they know
he would
be,
his
heart
would be
merry?
It's because
it was the
end of
the
dressing,
he's a wealthy
dude.
He's an old
guy and he's
been working
outside in the
field all day
with his
men and
they don't
have a
five-year
person.
So,
at the end
of the day,
he's drinking
the laundry,
he's lurking,
right?
It's the
standard of
his room and
they don't
have security
cameras.
So,
his men are
sleeping in a
circle around
his field and
he sleeps in
a giant pile
of wealth
from the
dressing floor
having drunk
his fill
after hard
things work
there's
never been
a happier
landing,
right?
And he's
just,
he's had a
good day's
work,
he's finished,
he's reaped
all this
grain and
at that
moment,
man,
that's not
a good
moment to
approach him
and ask
for a
favor,
right?
Reef clearly
makes himself
as attractive
as possible
and he
comes and
lays down
and says
to him,
I'll do
anything
you want,
right?
And at
that moment
he could
have stood
up and
betrayed
her and
ran around
her as
sound
reared
her
reputation,
right?
He could
have reached
her.
And if you
don't
think that's
a possibility,
you should
read
Judges.
You know,
with prayer,
that's a
disturbing
book.
He could
have just
treated her
in the
prostitute and
paid her for
services
periodically to
keep,
to help her
in their own,
right?
that's absolutely
would have
done this.
He could
have seen
her as a
country
bank,
which is
very normal
to think.
He could
have brought
her into
his house,
paid for
her daily
life,
and given
him no
hope,
no future,
right?
She has no
inheritance with
him,
she has no
legal authority,
she's just
living in part
of his
household.
It was a
very realistic
possibility.
But Naomi
hoped,
and had
brought
Reese to
hope,
that he
would act
better than
that.
And so
in this
moment when
no one's
looking,
when he
has absolute
control of
the situation,
he wakes up
in the middle
of the night,
and in the
moment his
robe is
getting pulled
up,
and by the
way,
people argue
about how
far they
pulled the
robe up.
It doesn't
take very
far,
right?
If you're
sleeping down
and you're
tracking along
something,
of course,
the robe
up a little
bit,
the implication
has been
made,
so I don't
get mad
or something
right?
This has
happened,
he's
awakened,
and he
has a
decision to
in the
middle
of the
night that
changed the
course of
life for
these two
women,
right?
He said,
oh,
don't do
this,
right?
Here's what
I want to
do.
I want you
to just
wait still
a bit in
the morning
when you
will be
safe and
there won't
be a
scandal,
and we'll
get you
out of
here in
the
morning,
and then
I'll
go and
do
everything
required to
make
this
legal and
proper,
and then
yes,
absolutely
can't.
Now,
here's a
man.
Can you just
have a
massive
change of
fortune,
and to
take two
interviews
into his
house within
18 hours
because he's
sufficiently
hopeful by
what reason
he's known.
He also
is anticipating
a good
future,
right?
But I'd like to
draw your
attention to what
he does
when he
sends her
away.
He doesn't
just send
her
into
handed.
He does
have
problems
for
something
and
reason.
He says,
I want
you to
take some
grain back
with you
when you
go.
Because it
reveals to
us in
this moment
that he
knows he's
not talking
to the
room.
He knows
he's
talking to
the
woman,
right?
And he
cares about
the whole
family.
He's just
not looking
for the
players
alone.
And so
he gives
six
raises
of
grain.
It's an
possibly
large
amount
of
grain.
It's
saying he
had to
carry it
on her
back.
And historians
today doubt
that it could
have been
six measures
by the way
in the
measure that
she would
have
made to
be a
donkey
to carry
it.
There was a
massive amount
of grain
that he
gave her
to carry
back.
But what he
gave her,
this is the
question for,
what he
gave her
was six
measures
of
need to
take back
time.
The hope
is in the
seed.
He's
promised
that your
fields
will grow
grain
again.
Your house
will have
seed again.
The hope
for the future
will be
restored to you
because hope
is always in
the seed.
And this is a
balance of seed
I'm giving
to you.
Your future
will be
restored and
you need to
stop being
hopeless.
I will
take care of
you in
the hand
of your
roof.
The bearing
despair,
and so what
Boaz does is
there's another
redeemer.
This is another
reason he didn't
have to do
this.
There was a
closer
redeemer.
There's him,
by the way,
had been
after.
There's a guy
who,
by rights,
should have
stepped in
earlier.
And what
he's supposed
to do by
law is sort
of be ahead
of two
households,
but I'm
sure of the
household
leader.
So he's
supposed to
take the
wife of
his relative
and have a
child with
her, but
then he can
carry on
the family
line.
The difficulty
in that is
if he does
that, he's
splitting his
effort and
his investment
between his
inheritance for
his family
and the
inheritance for
somebody else.
There's a lot
of effort
going in.
And so the
other two
of them were
told in chapter
four, you
don't want
to do
that.
And in
chapter three
of us, Boaz
actually kind
of played
it over it.
Boaz is
team group.
He's impressed
with her
integrity.
He's impressed
with her
work ethic
and she's
clearly hot,
you know.
And because
he's actually
within 18
hours, but
he goes to
the other
guy and he
says, hey,
you've heard
about the
moabite.
He doesn't
say the
attractive lady
he says
that moabite,
right?
And if you
buy the
rights to
the world
on the
one's
writing, you're
going to
have to
bury that
moabite.
You don't
want to
do that,
do you?
And the
guy says,
no, he's
like, oh,
okay, I'll
take one for
the team.
And you
go, I'll
go.
And it's
real.
And so
you can go
back in
Mary Ruth.
And it's
this moment
of
incredible
kindness.
Where is
God
mentioned
in the
book of
Ruth?
Only a
couple of
times when
now this
is God's
abandoned
me,
right?
And when
Ruth says,
I love
God for
me,
and the
Lord says,
may God
bless you.
There's no
actual direct
evidence of
God moving.
God's
movement is
in the
absence of
Boaz.
Right?
The result of
this in
verse 4,
3, 3,
17,
maybe.
Boaz
agreed,
she became
his wife.
He went
into her,
and the
Lord enabled
her to
continue to
give birth
to his
son.
And the
tragedy is
the
brother,
right?
There's
no future
for the
family.
The
women said,
blessed is
the Lord
who has
not left
you without
a redeemer
together.
Who's the
redeemer
here?
Boaz,
right?
Boaz
is acting
the part
of God
by just
simply doing
the lawful
thing,
just being
a righteous
deed.
May his
name become
famous in
Israel.
May he
also be
to your
restorer
of life
and sustainer
of your
old age.
For your
daughter-in-law
who loves
you is
better to
you than
seven sons
and then
Naomi took
the child
and laid
him in
the lap
and became
the nurse.
And the
neighbor
and the
woman gave
him a
name saying,
a son has
been born
to Naomi.
And so
the
burden of
chapter 1
is replaced
with the
joy of
chapter 4
with the
present as
he planted
in the
future of
the family.
And let's
see,
Boaz
is that
right in
his
simple
self's
act
spades
the lives
of 40
and 10
year old
women,
two women
who were
just sitting
in a
bedroom
seat.
I don't
think you
have
realized
this
has
read it
before.
Do you
know who
Boaz
bought the
rights
to find
that
land
from?
Naomi.
He took
the
boatload
of
cash.
So this
you can
have a
future
itself.
So here's a
future.
But not
only that,
the punchline
of
Ruth is
in the
end of
7th
chapter 1
verse
verse 17.
So they
named the
child Obed
and he's
the father
of Jesse
and he's
the father
of David.
So Ruth
became the
grandmother
of David.
King David.
You're right
he knows what
that means
in the context
of judges.
This time
was lawlessness
so there was
no king
and every
man did
what was
right in
his own
eyes.
First of
all,
Boaz
didn't do
what was
right in
his own
eyes.
He
followed
the
law of
Lord.
Right?
And as
a result of
that,
he raised
up the
family,
we saw
that as
the right
way to
live.
So the
three generations
down there
was a
son born
who had
offered
teams to
reinstate
the law
of the
Lord and
the land
was
sustained
from all
the barbarism
and all
the tragedy
and the
crisis
that had
been
recorded
in
Judges.
When
Boaz
did
this
simple
act of
honesty
and
kindness
from
the
Lord,
he
saved
his
nation
quite
literally.
Had
you not
done
that,
there
would
never
have
been
a
household
in which
David
was born
that brought
Israel back
from the
brink of
his extinction
and it
found him
the kingdom.
It's
incredible.
I mean,
he had no
idea on the
floor that night
when he was
offered an
opportunity that
many, many
wouldn't refuse
and at that
time it
started to
imagine
winning the
season.
He had no
idea he was
actually going to
change the
world,
but he did
by simple
act of
kindness.
And
if you
can do
nothing
else,
raise up
your household
of
righteousness
so that
three generations
from now,
they have
the
backbone
and the
capacity
to save
the world.
That's what
this tells
you.
That's the
hope for the
future that
you're
finding in
the
present.
Okay?
And beyond
that,
you guys
probably know
this,
to tie in
to the
manger,
the
decision
of David,
Christ,
right?
All this
promise,
all this
hope for
the future,
the restoration
of creation,
not just
Israel,
was to be
fulfilled by
the defending
of David,
the Messiah,
who would
be born,
we celebrate
now on
Christmas,
a seed
planted that
would grow
the kingdom
of God
on earth,
that would
bear the
fruit that
we are
today,
right?
We are
literally
sitting here
today because
Boaz was
unreasonably
nice one
night.
It's
true.
And he
acted
rightfully
when nobody
was looking.
He didn't
miss you.
No one
would have
thought worse
of him if
he had
kicked the
mollabies
to the curb
of the time,
right?
He actually
took a little
hook by doing
this thing
that was
kind of
awkward,
personally.
But he
proved the
course of
history.
All of
Christianity,
800 generations
from the
kingdom
were enabled
by the birth
of Christ,
of David,
by the
act of
God.
He planted
a seed
that's still
growing today.
And that
is what
hope is
about.
The
anticipation
of this
seed
growing
fruit
and
that's
fruit
playing
more,
which
grows
more
fruit,
which
plants
more.
That's
the hope
we have.
That's
the hope
that it's
not
ridiculous
to
hope
in.
You
don't
need to
keep
considering
like
in
sister's
faith,
I'm
just
working
really
hard.
No,
how can
we live
in that
hope?
In
Romans 5
having
been
justified
by faith,
we exult
in the
hope of
the
glory
of
God
and
not
just
only
but
we
also
exult
in
our
tribulations
knowing that
means about
perseverance.
Perseverance
means about
character.
Character,
hope.
That was kind
of the
story of
Ruth,
right?
And that
hope is
not
disappointing.
Because the
love of God
has been
poured out
within our
hearts
through the
Holy Spirit
that was
given to
us.
We have
a hope
that was
not
disappointing.
Peter calls
it our
living hope.
Right?
So living hope
is the seed
planted that
grows and
lives within
us.
Blessed
be the
God and
Father of
our
Lord
Jesus
Christ
in
1 Peter
1-3
who
according
to
his
great
mercy
has
caused
us
to be
born
again
into
a
living
hope
through
the
resurrection
of
Christ
Jesus
who
was
the
colonel
of
sea
planted
in the
ground
and he
sprang up
and had
a great
harvest
of whom
we were
one.
So in
this season
of hope
and it's
especially
this is a
time of
year when
we take
our kids
out and
we tell
them to
buy a
present
for their
brother and
their sister
and their
mother and
we wrap it
with them
and what's
the best
gift and
we put
them to
see and
we wait
in anticipation
of them to
open that
gift.
It's when
we teach
our kids
to give
good
gifts.
in memory
of the
time when
Christ did
the same
things.
God did
the same
thing for
us in
Christ.
The time
of hope
that we
have during
the Advent
anticipation
will pay
off and
we teach
them to
give
good
gifts.
That's
what the
presents
represent.
And I
would like
us to
do one
extra
thing.
This is
our
hope.
I'm going
to give
your
homework
to
look
forward
to.
It's
all
about
anticipations.
We have
homework.
The only thing
that's in the
first season
is always
be ready
to give
a count
of the
hope
that's
in you.
Right?
A lot
of times
that's
interpreted
to be
ready
with
solid,
rigorous,
intellectual
arguments
to prove
your
right.
And that
is not
what it
says.
It
says give
a count
of the
hope
that's
in
you.
Right?
Why are
you hopeful?
you need
to be
able to
save it.
And I
think we
all
probably
can
that you're
not
happy.
So your
homework
is look
at the
person.
It doesn't
have to
be the
person
next to
you.
You need
to
look and
pick
somebody
else.
And by
the way,
there's
several
possible
people here.
There's
several
people here,
right?
You might
not have
hope.
In which
case,
you still
need to
look and
find
somebody
to
tell you
about
the
hope
that's
in
them.
Right?
If you
need to
actually
write
down
why
you
have
hope
in
you.
What
is
the
hope
that
you
know
will
not
disappoint.
And
if
you
can't
write
well,
a song,
do
interpretive
dance,
I don't
care.
But you
need to
find a way
to express
the hope
that's in
you in
a way
that's
persuasive
to others
because it's
here.
You don't
have to
worry about
whether
they're
going to
believe
you.
You don't
have to
worry
about
whether
it's
persuasive.
You have
to worry
about
why the
hope
is
actually
in
you.
The
hope
that
you're
looking
forward
to
before
coming
to
share
it
with
somebody.
Google the
wall.
Okay.
And
we're not
going to
live a
lottery ticket
life.
I used to
think lottery
tickets were
attacks on
mathematical
altitude.
I
cynically
thought it
was really
funny that
people that
were good
at math
charged a
dollar
a try
to get
more money
to pay
for more
math
education.
I just
thought
that
it was
cynical
and then
really
funny.
But
I was
going to
decide
to
touch
on
hope.
Right?
I talked
in the
beginning
how
somebody
said
I hope
it
goes
well
and
didn't
sound
like
in
minute.
We're
so
embarrassed
of hope
we don't
use
hope
accurately.
We say
I hope
it works
This is
a genuine
hope that
we anticipate
the outcome.
That's what
you're writing
down.
It's not
lottery tickets.
It's why
you have
actual hope
that we're
not going to
be the
support.
That's your
own work.
Let's
pray.